Up until now you learn about generating a sequence of configurations
ここまでは A* や Hybrid A* などのアルゴリズムを使って
for vehicle using algorithms like A* and Hybrid A*.
車両の構成のシーケンスを生成することを学んできました
We refer to this as path planning. But what about time?
これをパスプランニングといいますでも時間はどうでしょうか?
In path planning, we imagine taking
パスプランニングでは ドライビング面と長さを
our driving surface and length some sort of discretized grid on top of it.
その上にある ある種の離散グリッドと想像します
Then, we make plans by specifying a start state and a goal state.
そして 開始状態と目標状態を指定してプランを作成します
And the trajectories we generate looks something like this for algorithms like A*
生成するトラジェクトリーは A* のようなアルゴリズムではこのようなもので
or something like this for algorithms like Hybrid A*.
Hybrid A* のようなアルゴリズムではこのようなものになります
These algorithms play an important role in autonomous driving.
これらのアルゴリズムは自動運転では重要な役割を担います
But the path they generate don't really take predictions into account.
でも 生成される経路は予測をあまり考慮しません
For example, let's project back to when the blue vehicle first wanted to change lane.
たとえば 青い車両が最初に車線を変えたかったときに戻ってみましょう
Here we will include the time as a third dimension.
ここで時間を 3 つ目の次元として含めます
One way to visualize it is to imagine looking at the road
これを視覚化する 1 つの方法は 道路をある角度から見ている
from some angle and time would be the dimension going up.
と想定し 時間は上にいく次元であるとします
And one way for a vehicle to move along the path that goes around the start vehicle,
車両が開始車両の周りを通る経路に沿って移動する
would be something like that.
1 つの方法はこのような感じのものです
The fast moving vehicle we perceived behind us is predicted to
後ろにいると認識した高速で移動する車両は
move in on the lane at a fast speed which would look something like that.
高速で車線に接近すると予測されます これはこのような感じです
And that's how we know that we cannot change lane immediately.
ですから 私達はすぐに車線を変更できないとわかります
If we try to go before the vehicle that passed us,
追い越された車の前 つまり 2 次元の
which is another red Polygram in the two dimension.
別の赤色のポリグラムに行こうとした場合
We will collide with the vehicle.
私達はこの車両と衝突するでしょう
We have to wait for this vehicle to drive past us.
この車両が私達を通り過ぎるのを待つ必要があります
Once the Red car has passed us,
赤い車が通り過ぎたら
we can proceed with our lane change
私達は車線変更に進むことができます
Now as you can see, having a path is nice,
これでおわかりのように 経路があることはよいのですが
but it is not sufficient to solve the planning problem when there are
自動運転している動的物体が常に周りにあるときには
dynamic objects around us which in autonomous driving is all the time.
プランニングの問題を解決することは十分ではありません
Therefore, we have to plan not only a sequence of configuration,
そのため 構成のシーケンス s d θ だけではなく
sd and fita but also have these configurations all set up in time.
これらの構成がすべて遅れないように設定する必要もあります
The trajectory is a function which for
トラジェクトリーは任意の時間 t が
any time t associates a configuration of a vehicle.
車両の構成を関連付ける関数です
Now, we need a way to generate such a trajectory.
今度は このようなトラジェクトリーを生成する方法が必要です
And the way we're going to do this,
これを行う方法では
is by separating the planning we do in the S dimension,
s 次元で行うプランニングを
from the planning we do in a d dimension.
d 次元で行うプランニングと分けます
Instead of thinking about one picture in three dimension,
3 つの次元のある 1 つの図を考えずに
we usually decide to reason about two pictures.
通常 2 つの図を推論します
Each of which is in two dimensions.
それぞれか 2 つの次元の図です
I'm going to walk you through
前のビデオでやった車両の追跡演習
the same vehicle tracking exercise I did in the previous video, two more times.
と同じものをあと 2 回見ていきます
One for s and one for d. Let's start with s. At t=0.
1 つは s で もう 1 つは dのものです まず s から始めます t=0 のとき
The vehicle is here at s=0.
ここの車両は s=0 です
Then at t=1, it's here.
t=1 のときここです
And it keeps moving until it reaches the situation where it goes to a full stop.
そして 完全に停止する状況に達するまで動き続けます
Note that we can see the vehicle has stopped by looking at this graph.
このグラフと見ると 車両が停止したことがわかります
Here we can see a flat slope and the flat slopes means no movement.
ここで 傾きがフラットになっており これは動きがないことを表します
This is something we couldn't see in that t
これは 経路を表すために前に使用した
over s graph that we used before to represent a path.
s と比較した t のグラフで見られなかったものです
Then the vehicle starts moving again until it reaches its final configuration at t=15.
次に車両は t=15 の最終構成に達するまで再び動き出します
Now, let's do the same thing for d versus
t に対する d について同じことをしましょう
t. As we move along the road, d remains constant.
道路に沿って進むと d は一定のままです
Then the vehicle goes to a full stop and after the stop, start shifting left.
そして車両は完全停止し 停止後左に移動を始めます
And after it has passed the green vehicle,
緑色の車両を抜かした後
it goes back to its original lane.
元の車線に戻ります
Finally, we can look at both trajectories
最後に 両方のトラジェクトリーを同時に
simultaneously and the great thing is that we can
見ることができます すごいことに
finally visualize the whole motion of the car over time.
車の動き全体を時間の経過とともに視覚化できます
It's not just a path now,
これは単に経路ではなくトラジェクトリーとなり
it's a trajectory and we can fully describe what the vehicle did within these 15 seconds.
この 15 秒間で車両がどう動いたかを完全に示すことができます
Next, I'm going to ask you to think about some questions involving graphs like these.
次に 皆さんにこれらのようなグラフに関係した質問をしようと思います